Guide to Commercial Closet, Ad Respect, and Michael Wilke LGBT Advertising Archive MSS.495
Fales Library and Special Collections
Commercial Closet, AdRespect, and Michael Wilke LGBT Advertising Archive
1975-2017
Fales Library and Special Collections
Wilke, Michael
MSS.495
20.5 Linear Feet in 19 record cartons, 1 manuscript box, and 1 oversize flat box
1 websites in 1 archived website.
Founded in 2001, the Commercial Closet Association, renamed AdRespect, began as a way to track and document lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender (LGBT) themed advertisements globally. Michael Wilke, the founding executive director of the Commercial Closet Association, has researched and written about LGBT issues in advertising for over twenty years. The print and media publications' series consists of mostly earmarked magazines and newspaper articles that were a part of Michael Wilke and the Commercial Closet Association's research ranging from 1975-2017. The photograph series is comprised of Wilke's personal photographs of family reunions, vacations and LGBT community events. The archived website contains a database of video and print advertisements rated by AdRespect dating back to 1917.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents the efforts of the Commercial Closet Association to collect and analyze domestic and international print and media advertisements that engage the LGBT community in positive and negative ways. The collection is comprised of two series: print and media publications and photographs. The print and media publications' series consists of mostly earmarked magazines and newspaper articles that were a part of Michael Wilke and the Commercial Closet Association's research ranging from 1975-2017. Major publications included within this series include Pride, Passport, Out, Outtraveler, Attitude, The Advocate, Genre, and The New York Times. The photograph series is comprised of Wilke's personal photographs of family reunions, vacations and LGBT community events. The collection also includes the website for AdRespect, with a library of LGBTQIA+ themed advertising and their AdRespect ratings.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: Series I: Print and Media Publications; Series II: Photographs; and Series III: Archived Website. The materials in Series I are arranged chronologically and by publication title. The materials in Series II are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Biographical Note
Michael Wilke has researched and documented the marketing of lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender (LGBT) themed advertisements as a business journalist and nonprofit leader since 1992. Wilke is the founding executive director of the Commercial Closet Association, which began in New York City in May 2001. The Commercial Closet Association, now renamed AdRespect, continues its mission to promote "advertising that respects diversity, gender identity/expression, and sexual orientation for a more accepting society and better business results." Wilke studied journalism at the School of Visual Arts in New York City, and earned a masters of marketing at Zicklin Business School of Baruch College-City University of New York. Previously, he worked as a business reporter at Advertising Age and has written about LGBT advertising and media for The New York Times, Adweek, Brandweek, The Advocate, Haymarket's Revolution marketing magazine, and Inside Media. He received the Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation (GLAAD) Media Award and was one of OUT Magazine's OUT 100 in 2001. Wilke has served as an advertising judge for the ANA Multicultural Excellence Awards, a Crain Lecturer at Northwestern University's Medill School of Journalism, and was a Hearst Professional in Residence fellowship at the University of Colorado at Boulder.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers. Appointments are necessary for the use of manuscript and archival collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Michael Wilke in June 2017. The accession number associated with this gift is 2017.054.
In 2016, https://www.adrespect.org/ was selected by curators and captured through the use of Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the special.collections@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Commercials.; Advertisements.; Advertising -- United States.; LGBTQ+ activism; Magazines (Periodicals); Gay rights movement.; Gay men -- United States -- Social life and customs.; Gay men.; Gays in popular culture.; Gays -- Political activity -- New York (State) -- New York.; LGBTQ+ people; LGBTQ+ communities
- Series I. Print and Media Publications, 1975-2017
  Scope and Contents
  The print and media publications' series consists of mostly earmarked magazines and newspaper articles that were a part of Michael Wilke and the Commercial Closet Association's research ranging from 1975-2017. Publications included within this series include Pride, Passport, Out, Outtraveler, Attitude, The Advocate, Genre, and The New York Times.
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged by publication title and date.
  - The Advocate, 1992-2017 (Box 1, Box 2, Box 3, Box 4, Box 5)
  - Genre, 1999-2008 (Box 5)
  - TETU (France), 2003-2010 (Box 6, Box 7)
  - After Dark, 1975-1979 (Box 7, Box 8)
  - Passport, 2002-2017 (Box 6, Box 12, Box 13)
  - Out, 1994-2017 (Box 8, Box 9, Box 10, Box 11)
  - Outtraveler, 2003-2008 (Box 12)
  - Metrosource, 2000-2007 (Box 12)
  - Attitude (UK), 2000-2006 (Box 14)
  - Fight 4 Sight (Box 14)
  - GLAAD Publications, 2006-2008 (Box 14)
  - Various Publications (Box 14, Box 16, Box 17, Box 18, Box 19)
  - Abercrombie and Fitch Quarterly, 1997-2003 (Box 15)
  - Instinct, 2005-2008 (Box 15)
  - Blue, 2002 (Box 15)
  - Luerzer's, 2005 (Box 15)
  - Pride, 1999-2005 (Box 19)
  - GUS, 2008 (Box 19)
  - Gay Times, 2000-2005 (Box 19)
  - T: The New York Times Style Magazine, 2005-2010 (Box 19)
  - Gay Pages, 2006-2008 (Box 19)
  - Advertisement Clippings' Scrapbook (Box 20)
- Series II. Photographs, 1986-2003 (Box 21)
  The photograph series is comprised of Michael Wilke's personal photographs of family reunions, vacations and LGBT community events. Most of the photographs in this series range between 1986-2003. There are four folders with undated photographs, which are most likely from the early to mid 1900s.
- Series III. Archived Website, February 2016-ongoing; 1 websites in 1 archived website.
  Accruals
  New site crawls are accrued quarterly.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
  AdRespect was founed by Michael Wilke in 1996, initially known as the Commercial Closet Association. The website is a database of thousands of print and video advertising related to the gender identity and sexual orientation, dating back to 1917 from all over the world. AdRespect rates the majority of advertisement with a score based on the inclusiveness and respectfulness of the advertisement toward the LGBTQIA+ community. Advertisements directed toward LGBTQIA+ audiences are intentionally not rated. The website also includes best practices for ad creators. The website underwent a major redesign in 2023.